Hello
네 안녕하세요
In today's session
어 금일 세션은요
We'd talk a little bit about how Ubuntu is being provided in various cloud environments.
이제 다양한 클라우드 환경에서 우분투가 어떻게 제공되고 있는지 좀 얘기를 해볼까 합니다.
We are Junhyun Bae of Cloud Mate, Sejun Kim. It's nice to meet you (nice to meet you)
저희는 클라우드 메이트의 배준현 김세준 입니다 네 반갑습니다(반갑습니다)
Here, it's a topic we're going to talk about today
자 어 저희가 오늘 얘기할 주제인데요
Can you explain about it briefly?
어 얘기할 주제에 대해서 간략하게 한번 설명 해주시겠습니까?
You pass it like that(laughs)
그렇게 넘어가면 되는 군요(웃음)
It's giving or receiving, and it's in English
주거니 받거니 하는거죠. 영어로 되어 있어서
We are a cloud service provider, and we provide services to cloud to cloud venders.
예, 저희는 이제 클라우드 서비스의 벤더사에서 이제 서비스를 제공하고 있는 클라우드 서비스 프로바이더이고요
And we consult users no matter they are on AWS, Azure or Google.
저희가 이제 AWS나 Azure, Google 이런식으로 이제 벤더사에 크게 상관없이 이제 사용자들의 이제 그 컨설팅을 진행 해드리는데요.
Now, what we want to focus on here is that when we're using Linux,
여기서 이제 저희가 이 중점을 두고 싶은 것은 이제 리눅스를 사용을 한다고 했을 때
Ubuntu deliverd by Canonical is the most being supported operating system supported by the 3 companies.
이제 각 3사에서 가장 많이 지원을 하고 있는 운영체제가 이제 우분투, Canonical에서 제공하는 우분투라는거죠.
So, each vendor is now focusing on different operating systems, but
그래서 각각의 이제 벤더사마다 이제 중점을 두고 있는 이제 운영체제가 다 다르지만
For Canonical's Ubuntu which all three provide in common, we are explaining a little more detail what kind of service the vendor provides and how does it deliverd.
셋 다 공통적으로 제공하고 있는 Canonical의 우분투에 대해서 조금 더 벤더사에서 어떤 서비스를 어떻게 제공하고 있는지 조금 더 상세히 알아 보고자 합니다.
As you said, now let's find out how Ubuntu is being provided by three famous companies in the cloud.
일단 말씀 주신 것 처럼 이제 클라우드에서 유명한 3사에게서 좀 우분투는 어떻게 제공되고 있는지 알아볼까 합니다.
First of all, oh, we didn't introduce ourselves before that.
첫번째는 아, 그전에 저희 또 소개를 안했네요
To introduce myself, I'm Bae Junhyun, and I'm currently the head of the Seoul branch of Ubuntu Korean Commnnity.
소개를 하자면 저는 배준현이고요 현재 우분투 한국 사용자 그룹에서 서울 지부장을 맡고 있습니다.
And I work as an Azure MVP at Microsoft and work on DevOps.
그리고 마이크로소프트에서 Azure MVP로 활동하고 있고 DevOps 관련으로 일을 하고 있습니다.
Yes, I operate a community called Smart Azure Living in Korea
예, 저는 한국에서 이제 슬기로운 Azure 생활이라는 커뮤니티를 운영하고 있고요
I also work as an Azure MVP and I work as a cloud architect.
마찬가지로 Azure MVP로 활동하고 있고 저는 이제 클라우드 아키텍트로 활동하고 있습니다.
Then, let's talk about Azure, which we are a bit confident of among the three cloud companies.
자 그러면 클라우드 3사 중에 일단 저희가 좀 자신있는 Azure 관련해서 한번 좀 얘기를 해볼게요.
In the case of Azure, the logo has changed a bit recently. The logo has changed, and
Azure 같은 경우에는 최근에 로고가 좀 바뀌었습니다. 로고가 바뀌었고
we do not need to find Ubuntu to use Ubuntu on Azure now, we are now
어 저희가 Azure에서 이제 우분투를 사용하시려면 딱히 우분투를 찾으실 필요가 없이
providing the latest LTS version of Ubuntu as
이제 'Create a resource', 그니까 virtual machine을 생성할 때에
it is, 'Create a resource', as you can see when we create a virtual machine.
이렇게 보시는 화면처럼 우분투의 최신 LTS 버전을 그대로 제공을 하고 있습니다.
It provides the version corresponding to 'focal fossa' as it is.
'focal fossa'에 해당하는 버전을 그대로 제공을 하고 있구요
Sometimes, there's some people who want to use a different version of the image, who want to use a lower image to be more stable.
혹시나 내가 다른 버전의 이미지를 쓰고 싶다 좀 더 낮은 이미지를 좀 stable 하게 원하시는 분들 가끔 있으세요
So, if you want to use a lower version, you can create a virtual machine like
그래서 낮은 버전을 쓰고 싶다라고 하시면 이렇게 virtual machine을 생성을 할 때에
let's enlarge this guy
이 친구 살짝 한번 확대를 해볼까요
You can use the lower version such as 'bionic beaver' or
뭐 조금 더 낮은 버전 'bionic beaver'라던지 뭐 다른 버전 그리고
you can also use the Linux other versions as we can see.
또 보시다 싶이 또 다른 그 리눅스 버전들도 같이 이용을 하실 수가 있으세요.
In addition, when you want to get some support from Canonical
추가적으로 이제 Canonical에 서포트를 받고 싶다라고 했을 때
you can search for Canonical on the Marketplace to find various versions, and
이제 Marketplace에서 Canonical이라고 검색을 하시면 다양한 버전을 확인할 수가 있고
in the case of this guy, a bit of price should be charged.
이 친구 같은 경우에는 이제 charge가, 비용이 charge가 약간 됩니다.
If you want to check the Pro licenses that are now fully serviced by Canonical, you should search for Canonical on the Marketplace.
Canonical의 정식 서비스를 받으시는 Pro 라이선스를 이제 확인하고 싶으신 분들은 Marketplace에서 Canonical을 검색하시면 됩니다.
Yes, and there's a 'reserved instance'
예, 그리고 이제 실제 그 'reserved instance'라고 해서
Which can be reserved Canonical delivering instances for 1~3 years
이제 Canonical의 서비스를 받는 인스턴스를 1년 혹은 3년 동안 예약을 할 수 있는데요
then you can also get some discount option about 15% for these reservations.
그 예약을 했을 때에 라이선스 비용을 조금 더 할인 받을 수 있는 옵션도 지금 하고 있습니다. 한 15% 정도 할인이 될겁니다.
In the case of Azure, most of the backend technologies are very well connected with Canonical (Yes, it is)
Azure 경우에는 대부분의 백엔드 기술을 케노니컬과 상당히 연계가 잘 되어 있어요(네 그렇죠)
It differ by the each cloud company, though you should regard Azure is being supporeted as Debian or Ubuntu like.
각 클라우드사마다 다르긴 한데 이제 Azure는 대부분 이제 데비안 계열 혹은 우분투 계열로 지원을 받고 있다고 생각을 해주시면 되겠어요.
So even if you run Cloud Shell, there is now another operating system for Ubuntu.
그래서 클라우드 쉘을 실행해줘도 이제 우분투에 대한 운영체제가 또 있고요.
Next, it's AWS
다음에 이제 AWS인데요
Now, if you scroll down a bit on the first screen when you create an actual instance
AWS도 이제 실제 인스턴스를 생성할 때 가장 처음에 나오는 화면에서 스크롤을 약간 내려보시면
it now supports Ubuntu Server
이제 우분투 서버에 대한 내용을 이제 지원을 하고 있고요
and it supports 64-bit or ARM
기본적으로 64비트나 이제 ARM
it supports x86 and ARM of 64-bit.
64비트에 x86이나 ARM을 지원하고 있습니다.
And there's another license for these servers when you search for it
그리고 이제 검색을 해보시면 마찬가지로 Azure랑 마찬가지로 이제 그 서버들을 제공할 수 있는 라이센스가 또 별도로 있고요
and here you see 62% saving in order to get a 62% saving
이제 여기 보시면은 이제 이쪽도 62% saving이라고 있는데 62% saving을 받으시려면
you have to sign to 'you must keep to use about 1~3 years'.
역시 '1년 정도 혹은 3년 정도 그렇게 사용을 하셔야 한다'라는 그런 계약을 하셔야지만 이제 비용을 할인 구매 할 수 있으십니다.
In case of AWS, when you installed such Azamzon Linux, bacially
AWS 같은 경우에는 기본적인 그 AWS 리눅스라던지 뭐 Amazon Linux를 설치했을 때는
the package manager is a Debian familly, it actually provides Fedora familly
그 패키지가 데비안 계열은 아니죠 페도라 계열을 좀 제공을 하고 있고요
In case of Azure, it provides the Debian family
Azure 같은 경우에는 뭐 데비안 계열을 제공을 하고 있고
Lastly, here is Google
자, 이제 마지막으로 구글입니다
In case of Google, uh, it was a bit unique.
구글 같은 경우에는 어 약간 독특했었어요.
First of all, the Google console itself is rather simple.
일단은 구글 콘솔 자체가 좀 간단하긴 하죠.
It's simple, but as we saw earlier, you can still get a Pro license
간단하긴 한데, 저희가 앞에서 보셨던 바와 같이 Pro 라이선스도 여전히 받으실 수 있구요
and it offers all of the same existing LTSs.
똑같은 기존 LTS들을 다 제공하고 있습니다.
What differs in GCP is that you can see the lastest is deployed here
근데 GCP가 이제 두 가지 앞쪽에 얘기했던 것과 약간 다른 부분은 여기 보시면 최신 버전이 지금 올라와 있어요
Usually, they only provide LTSs, and the other 2 companies still don't support 21.04,
보통 보면 LTS 버전까지만 제공하는데 아직 3사 중에 앞에 설명드렸던 두 회사에서는 아직 21.04를 현재 제공을 하고 있지 않은데
while here, it support 'hirsute hippo' the 21.04.
여기선 최신 버전의 뭐였죠 hirsute hippo였나요 그 형태의 21.04를 제공하고 있고
In 21.04, the kernel version has been changed.
이제 21.04같은 경우에는 커널 버전이 바뀌었습니다.
In the 20.04, the 5.4 kernel was used, but if you want to use the 5.11 kernel, you can choose it.
기본 20.04에서는 5.4 커널을 썼었는데 5.11 커널까지 올라오는 사용하신다고 하면 선택하실 수가 있겠습니다.
Finally, we, Cloudmate structs and operate the real services for the member companies.
마지막으로 이제 저희 Cloudmate는요 이제 클라우드 맴버사에서 실제 서비스들을 구축하고 운영하는 것을 담당하고 있고요
and, some of you who use cloud, Wherever for you are using in,
여러분들께는 이제 클라우드는 사용하실 때 이제 3사에 대한 어느 곳을 사용하시든
if you use Linux, we recommond you to use Ubuntu
리눅스를 사용하신다면은 저희는 우분투를 활용키를 권장드리고 싶고요
and we highly encourage you to operate as same configurations and same environments.
우분투를 사용해서 여기저기 어떤 클라우드를 사용하시든 같은 운영으로 같은 환경으로 운영하시는 것을 적극 권장드리고
and it would be good to play with us for clouds.
저희와 함께 클라우드를 했으면 좋을 것 같습니다.
Yes, this was our explanation.
네, 여기까지 저희 설명이었습니다.
Nice to meet you. Oh, it's not 'nice to meet you'.
반갑습니다. 아, 반갑습니다가 아니지
Yes, thank you. It's been Cloudmate.
네, 감사합니다. 이제까지 Cloudmate였습니다.